[Music]
okay
uh our our topic um which was proposed
by alexander is the exodus versus the
lynch mob
and um and i was thinking about uh
i was thinking about heidegger and i was
thinking about his notion of
authenticity
and i was thinking about the authentic
person is the guy perhaps who joins the
exodus
am i getting that right alexander or
yeah
but especially with looking at
leadership so um
in digital libido john cena question i
identified the authentic phallus and the
fake phallus
the fake phallus leads uh
by arranging uh an objection so say you
got hitler and the jew you got started
in the kulak
you got um paul pott and anybody who
wore glasses in cambodia in the 1970s so
or it could be just woke today has the
white tetrasexual man
so you find somebody you can hate and
thereby in theory
unify everybody else into some kind of a
lynch mob
right so that's how lynch mobs operate
um
that's the fake fighter the authentic
follows though more difficult
and much more rare in history
unfortunately is the proper authentic
leader
now if you look at that's what we wanted
to study
the exodus for the new book and not just
the exodus out of egypt but all the
exodus
since we've been working with paradigm
shifts
our entire ubers all our books are about
the current paradigm shift essentially
that
what does it mean to leave industrialism
with capitalism and mass media and
and the life we sort of lived here and
moving to the new rom of the internet
society or or the internet age or the
network society
and digitalization what does that mean
and of course
a whole new class structural step
forward some people are better at or
more fortunate
when it comes to having the resources
that pay off in the new society we
identified that in the book called the
democrats 20 years ago
so all the work is about paradigm shifts
and a paradigm shift really is an exodus
out of one age
into a new age so
we call this exodology that's ex that's
what we
pursue in this book the theory on
exodus why do they happen why do they
tend to be so successful compared to the
alternatives which is of course our
lynch mobs and why do you leave a
certain territory say
the egypt of the lynch mob and you walk
into the promised land
of the exodus um and what does that say
of course this ties into the authentic
phallus of course leads the exodus of
moses for example
and the fake phallus who obviously leads
the lynch mob
and i don't know if this is part of
gerard's fantastic study on the lynch
mob
or not uh when he talks about satan
that is the tyrant to us and in our last
episode we talked about the accident the
tyrant
and the mob though right satan is the
spirit of the mob
no well the spirit of the mob is the
anoject so
what's important always is to find the
precursor to the phenomenon you're going
to study
so we can call all of this we can call
this paradigmatic
embryonism i suggested it to our dear
friend brady along the other day he
loved it so paradigmatic
embryonism means you study who was lucky
enough to be in the right place at the
right time before the paradigm started
or who saw it coming and could therefore
prepare for it
and was hungry enough to actually
benefit from it in other words who's the
hebrew in egypt and moses comes along
okay so the anoject
is clearly the lynch mob it's it's this
heideggerian dust man
so it's clearly the uh nobody actually
says it but
it's assumed like you know does man is
there is a heideggerian word for
inauthentic is that yeah like one rather
than you or i so
it's not somebody who speaks about
something i believe but rather
one believes oh i see and when you say
one belief you're hiding behind
something you say one believes in the
generals that's like
well i just believe like everybody else
because i'm a conformist and i'm scared
of being in the outside of the group
because i'm terrified of this i'm going
to pretend i'm part of it so i'm going
to participate in the lens mob and i do
that precisely by saying one believes
that that's the object that we're going
to kill
so you become the anonymous accuser
right
it doesn't really work in english
because one in english is still
you know even the queen of england could
say one or we whatever she says
but in german the term does man
not ma man with man with 2n m-a-n-n
which is just man
but man it's like it's very generous we
just
i don't know about or dutch thomas could
say that in swedish we have man as well
but
man say you saw instead of my i speak
you say man speak so you're hiding
behind something very honest
heidiger hated this right he he hated
his authentic behavior
but what he didn't see what this was
part of the very lunch bob that he
participated in himself he was the nazis
right
so the lynch mobs
are assuming not only that they have an
enemy they're gonna attack and kill
attorney to scapegoat
who's the abject but they also assume
that they have a shared
value a shared opinion within the group
called the architect
and all it takes is for somebody to put
on the right dress at the right time
and step forward and personify the
energetic and speak exactly what the
energetic would have said and you get an
art of hitler
and that's exactly what guys like out of
it to get to power so quickly because
everybody's like
yeah this is what we've been waiting for
just like you waiting for a savior
waiting for somebody to speak for us who
says what we want to say
who puts words what we want to say and
does so in a great uniform too
that's going to get the time so do you
think a figure like that is going to
appear
um or do you think there's a figure like
that already out there
oh yeah i'm i'm sure there's a bunch of
them or
all these woke people out there
especially young women who lead woke
today inspired to be
tyrants we wrote texts yeah but are any
of them like real leaders like
you know who who can who can get the
whole population behind them or
you know they don't need to get the
population behind them
you miss my point the reason why the
turret rises so quickly
is that he or she already like the
anarchic
okay that's exactly hitler didn't have
the hitler's
hitler's brigade were terribly
disorganized
the nazi party was never well organized
he was basically traveling around being
big on his ego at the time it was hard
to make decisions for hitler
at a terrible time that's why he started
taking impediments during the world
because he had fighted so hard to make
to see he was terrified of people to
make decisions
he wasn't at all a great leader no he
was just
personification of the anarchy with
germany coming out of the first world
completely sort of a great puppet of
some kind or
like not puppet either because that's
marinette that's being you you
know he knew what he was doing but he he
believed personally that he was the
personification of the german folk
and he was he was the personification of
the german lynch mob
i'm sure gerard would agree so when i
agree with gerard he calls this figure
satan we call him the tyrant
that's interesting because that's what
heidegger thought about him he would
personify the german that's why
heidegger got in trouble right
because in his early in his 30s he said
he said he said uh hitler personifies
the german people
yeah but he didn't he
an ejection theory yet the pointer is
that nobody's done that before under
we're doing pioneering work
we're trying to go deeper than chiron
did and by
by finding a precursor to gerard satan
a precursor to the tyrant historically
we have the antidote
now since this is inverted exodus we're
doing the lynch mob goes towards
zero it goes towards no space left it
goes
it goes towards staying within the realm
where you're at and then just minimizing
it
optimally until you die it's a doomsday
cult
hitlerism was a doomsday cult it was
either doomed to fail and he loved it
for it
so the question lynch mobs always are
that's why they're temporary they blow
up they cost
tons of havoc jacobins there was no way
the jacobins could ever run france
because all they did was guillotining
anybody including themselves
as a walk people would do too woke
people cannot lead
they can only destroy that's what lynch
mobs do
that's the problem with lynch mob in an
amoral sense
now the opposite of that is then the
exodus and since that's what we've been
working on for the past three to four
years
i thought it'd be a nice move in our
discussions here
especially you guys being more experts
on buddhism and gerard than i could ever
possibly be
could we then invert the inversion so
instead of doing inverted exonology
which is the theory of the lynchpop the
anaject to the target
what would exitology look like and
here's where it gets interesting because
we get a much more formal and
much wider and much more intense
authentic fatigue theory here
the theory of authentic phallus who's
that well the person's calling you
we can bring nietzsche into it right
that's that's the next step right
this one is where the messiah and the
ubermens are the same
they're all leaders of the accidents and
in the last discussion you said the
ubermensch was not one person you made
an interesting idea that the uber bench
should be more of a like a tribe or
something rather than moses
led the hebrews out of egypt they
rewrote the story later under his arrest
and personal influence in babylon
as the story of the three siblings moses
and aaron
lead and there's also miriam the sister
holding the brothers accountable for
what they do
that's exactly how mad turkey operates
in relation to patriarchy
and patriarchy is always the split
phallus okay
where did they learn that from they
learn that power must be shared and
divided
otherwise it becomes tyranny where is
the danger from the persians
who they learned that from solar raster
bishops we're back to the origin
of eventology which is so raster's idea
that he had vishnu
of split between the moabit and morbid
and the shanza
the king of kings and the priest of
priest must not be
unified they must be separated separate
courts separate capitals
separate system and then you can have a
supreme court to judge between them and
that's exactly what a matriarchy is
okay can i bring thomas in here thomas
do you have any comments so far
on what alexander said before it goes
further in the narrative very good model
um i'm not sure in
what way you go beyond gerard i mean
this all this is all very much within
the girardi and framework so far
um i really like the interpretation of
nietzsche's
over man as uh somebody who kind of
opposes the mop and kind of uh
points to a better direction so that's a
very positive
interpretation of the over man which is
usually like
you know interpreted as some kind of uh
some kind of uh
you know individualist diverse right
individual so that's a very nice
interpretation i think
and also i think it's it's kind of
important to
to investigate well what's that going to
be in a post ai post internet
society right what is going to lead us
there
it's probably going to be a group of
people or or so what's that going to
look like i think that's a very
very important question that's where the
exodus comes in i agree completely
that's what the exodus comes in
i don't see any reason at all why the
elite
of people the netocrats who are
successful communicating with the ai
and collaborate with the ai towards what
i call symbiotic transcendence
i don't see any reason why they would
drug the vast majority of people with
them
especially if they weren't gratefully
received to begin with
now the atonist cult of egypt that
became the origin of hebrewism and
eventually judaism
uh that left egypt clearly was a
minority under
some kind of oppression in egypt or at
least they didn't feel they were part of
the egyptian system at all
so you know tutankhamun was killed he
was probably the precursor to christ so
freud was probably right that the
activists of egypt and acton became
adonai
and adonai is the name when you unify
the other two facets of the jewish god
which is of course
eloah which is general for god and
you've got jave
and jave is the vulcan volcanic god of
the illamite so
so so that means edomites so that means
you've got a rain god in the sun god
within the same divinity again judaism
reflectives or asterism makes sense
uh so that's clearly the case with
judaism
now exodus means that a
minority hard and are aware what's going
on and can benefit from the new paradigm
leave
yeah so that's us we're the jews in
other words i mean
in the sense the the people who are well
not necessarily but the people who are
uh don't fit any in uh to egypt
don't belong in egypt or or for good or
bad but the puritans of england
and mayflower is the same story all over
it's a mimicking again gerard and
mimiking
of the exodus out of egypt that became
the exodus out of europe and it was
especially the exodus out of catholicism
away from the catholic church because
protestantism was hijacked by the states
in northern europe
and if you just wanted to be say a
non-state non-pope
christian person in europe you'd have to
become puritan or a protestant who was
on the line with the state
and of course it was precisely those
protestants in northern and western
europe
left for north america what they did was
that they then mimicked the exodus and
then later they come
in volga verses of it like the mormons
going to utah et cetera
so this story of exodus is constantly
repeating the exodus is always a small
minority you said
why are we treated like shit here okay
well we don't want to be part of this
society anyway we stuck so this is just
a bunch of locus of losers
let's leave so i think when we
looking at the interaction between human
beings and machines
as ai support and this is what thomas
knows way better than i do
i don't see any reason why the vast
majority of people will be
entitled to be part of that process of
the human machine interface
i would see that collaboration rather
being an elite group of people who are
very adapt at
specializing in what they do compared to
what the machine does well so if
the machines are very centered on logos
human beings should be very centered on
pathos
if i would be a machine i'd probably be
interested in a very sexy artist way
more than i'd be interested in a
logician or a mathematician
but i don't know i mean that's an open
question but i'd see an
exodus coming around the corner awesome
exit is out of woke
meaning the first places in the world
that says that we're woke free
we just got rid of the shit we stopped
guillotining people we just don't cancel
anybody any longer we
cancelled cancel culture itself we the
platform
did the platforming business you know
anybody does that today
would clearly signal that we know what's
going on that's wrong
and this would be a very welcoming place
for people to think
freely and express themselves freely
that's what's going to happen on the
global level at all it's certainly not
happening in america and probably not in
scandinavia so
you need new places where you can go to
think and speak
freely so you can become smart that's a
question
i have a question um usually the jews
are considered like slaves right
when they're in in egypt and and they
they
they they you know they
they're they're you're describing the
exodus
as as a bunch of elite people yeah i
know but
but the jews weren't a bunch of elite
people they were slaves right
no wait a second they were not slaves in
the current
afro-american woke sense they were
slaves in the marxist sense of
proletarians
i want to bring marx in here too yes no
this is why there's a connection between
marxism and judaism that's why karl marx
is a jew
the exodus story dominates jewish
culture immensely
right the three siblings are at the
center they regard the father son spirit
the father's son mother whatever
christianity has basically mimicking of
of the jewish triad so which is exactly
what it is
well my point is like i think the jews
jews symbolize the elite and also the
slave at the same time they have
the elite of the future so
you have a small minority they might
look oppressed now but they see
themselves
heroically yeah sure that is why i
always said the nietzsche's mistake was
to make the ubermensch a singular person
rather than a group of people which marx
did with the proletariat
now if you if you leave a lot of the
bullshit marks did you call us as marks
and rather marxist or whatever you like
let's not get into that at all let's let
let's let's leave marx to kill her or so
for us and
they can do the dirty business of their
life whatever they want so we can save
the idea of the proletariat the uberman
should at least be two
because then nietzsche is interested in
the savior the sausian
the messiah okay uh dan marx was
interested in who are the elite who
follow
the overman so really the over man
is the netocratic savior
and the proper proletariat that can only
happen
now couldn't have happened before
certainly not in lenin's moscow in 1918
uh can only happen now so marxism could
eventually be
realized as an exodus of an autocratic
elite
whether they leave physical space and go
into something more digital
or preferably they because they can
they take digital with them to certain
physical realms like estonia or the
czech republic or
or singapore or whatever what they can
do as they please
that's what i think is going to happen
next so we're going to see the beginning
of the exodus
into the digital that could be the title
of the book but because we owe so much
to
to hegel and whitehead we're going to
call the book process an event anyway
but you know otherwise so there's going
to be an exodus from the elites
basically from the netoccrates
basically okay so a small minority that
have a heroic idea of themselves that's
a proletariat
they're oppressed but they're oppressed
in a sense that that's okay we're
oppressed now because we're going to
rule the world in the future
and this is what we're going to set
about to do it that's the exact
opposite of woke victimhood nothing to a
victim
it's a it's slavery that will be turned
into mastery because the slaves are
dying to become masters now nietzsche
would love that
marx would love that white ted hegel
would certainly love that
and i don't see any reason oh well that
wouldn't happen i think that's very very
likely that we're going to get the small
elite to say that
okay let's see the restaurant and then
that elite will then be split into
three different sections a symbolic
natocracy
an imaginary autocracy and a real
autocasting real resources
and that's exactly what always happened
with previous power elites during
previous paradigms
so we're looking for the embryos of this
elite now meaning what we're doing with
our studies we're doing paradigmatic
embryonism
on the population the global population
as a whole now
back to the exodus so what is exodus
then exodus
is the teaching or the knowledge of
how to do a proper exodus what does it
mean to have an authentic fallacy leader
in what way does he or she lead or they
lead
and who are the elite following the
leader who perform the exodus
that then at best can be mimicked
by other peoples in the future to also
be successful
and that process is the process of
building education
okay creating proper leaders yeah
through proper
archetypal modes so the
associate according to the persians is
split
between the chieftain and the priest
yeah okay meaning mind and body are
separated this is the only duality
that so raster and is modernism allows
meaning the the later gnostic
misinterpretation of body mind must be
separate so that the mind can be
superior to the body
so the mind can be good and body can be
evil would be
awfully strange to sore asthma since he
didn't even have
the concepts of goodness and evil that
did not exist in persia 3
hundred years ago asha and rouge means
simply actually it's a constructive
mindset
and drought is a destructive mindset and
ruiz is
reversing it's like a grown-up wants to
be a child
asha is grown up who wants to become a
god
he completely needs you nietzsche was
more zoroaster than he ever could have
dreamed of
so that is where i want to base the
exodus and that's why i don't want to
have another ology
for the lynch mob i just want to call it
inverted
exodology so we realize exactly what it
is that it's a perversion
and an inversion of something incredibly
healthy and wonderful and it's probably
the worst thing human beings have ever
invented the lynch mob
yeah yeah well i it seems like we're
living in all these inversions right now
everything
seems very inverted like i have a
question still though and i brought up
the last time and i'm still working on
it and that is the concept of the martyr
okay yeah maybe thomas has some ideas
about that i i
yeah cause we have scapegoats right and
we have heroes and we have victims and
and we know the scapegoat is a very
elastic concept there are scapegoats
that are just completely innocent
being dragged along and thrown in for
good measure we have skateboards there
are clear objects so
we found a jew and we're not so let's
kill the jew right um
and we also know this is interesting we
also know that we can do whatever we
want with the scapegoat after we
killed him so there's a cynical way
using the scapegoat
kingdom sacred cynical way of doing it
but there are different things we can do
with the scapegoat we're basically we
basically do
free to do whatever we like with the
corpse aren't we and that
can be turned into a martyr right the
scapegoat right it can be turned into
anything because he can't defend himself
he's dead
so uh the usual process of
scapegoating is the scapegoat becomes
uh the mar the martyr or the isn't that
right
thomas from a girardian point of view no
no let's see the murderer
unless you guys have a theoretical
martyr coming from gerard let's see the
murder out for now
because the martyr is a very very very
complex phenomenon
and you know blowing my brains out of
the moment about the martyr
but the the the to begin with the
scapegoat can be used because it's a
corpse and that's exactly what the
egyptians do when they build the
pyramids
exactly it was only after the egyptians
started building the pyramids the
persons decided to build the drock bus
and the desert basically just put away
the corpses and say that a dead person
is a dead person is no longer there
souls gone so it's just dead
leave it to be eaten by the vultures so
we do not build pyramids because they
knew
that the pyramids would ruin egypt which
they did and they would be
they would be the ultimate turning i
think the construction of the pyramids
was the ultimate journey ever so there's
something about
preserving a corpse um
which which is yeah bound up with the
scapegoat mechanism
we need to go over where we're just
burning something it would mean you you
don't maybe you can jump in here so
the idea is that so so you have tensions
in the community right
so everybody decides the tensions and
the problems in our community
they are the fault of the scapegoat
which is some random person that can
easily be killed like typically a leper
or something like that
so the community gets angry at the
scapegoat kills the scapegoat
but during the killing there's this
orgastic
explosion of energy and after the
killing everybody is suddenly
relieved and the conflict is gone
because they've kind of projected
everything on that scapegoat right
but then the scapegoat is turned into
something holy
so that's why you have this strange
connection between
um turn the community turning against an
individual killing the individual and
afterwards that that individual that is
being killed is then turned into a holy
sacred object and that's that's kind of
a very core element of of gerard's
theory right and that
explains a lot of very strange rituals
where where kings are for example
uh um where where where people are first
uh
um um excluded killed and then and then
turned into objects of uh
of um of uh into religious objects right
into uh in
into uh virtu uh objects of uh
worshipping yeah this is very
interesting because that means this
connection between zoroastrianism and
christianity and two different ways of
dealing with the scapegoat mechanism
gerard is of course didn't studies or
astralism
so what they did was they just
they started to celebrate the paul
gazars and persia which is to celebrate
your memory for 70 years every day you
died
to die the day you died during the
during the year they would celebrate
your memory for 70 years if you were
worthy of it right if you're an
honorable person
which was a majority jews do that for a
year you you
yeah or whatever again shared culture so
they have obviously
influenced the way to do that was they
saw to avoiding building the pyramids
and ruining the economy and the pyramids
was what they wanted to do
because the pyramids were obviously
built to impress so if the dead
pharaoh be buried inside the pyramid
looking at the sun he'd still be alive
and he would rule from there or
something like that so they wanted to
avoid that and christianity
if gerard is correct dealt with it by
just making christ the ultimate
scapegoat
and put him on a cross and once he was
dead he died for all our sins
so nobody could no longer die for sins
that's why martyrs get interesting in
christianity for example
because marcus and christianity
obviously do not die for our sins
they become role models which christ was
not no no no no
you don't think so reward gerard has
written about this
so one of the characteristics of
christianity is that
jesus did it for you he did it yeah you
don't need to do it
and that's why the martyrs they expose
the the victimized mechanism so they
expose the devil so to say
right but they are not they're not
persons to copy
that's exactly what i said thomas i said
they they're not
persons to copy in their behavior there
their role models in character
meaning they stayed with the faith even
when they were under
suffering so so he's like you can be
christian
look at this guy he stayed with christ
he stayed with christ all the way
through
he did not die for your sins christ died
for his sins
well well the martyr is conscious of of
of what he's doing uh whereas the
scapegoat is just a victim
right yeah yeah okay we're talking
christian martyr here so let's wait
yeah the christian martyr knows he he he
holds on to the faith and he's
the whole time right yeah he's burnt
then he's burned at the stake whereas
the vic the
the scapegoat is just taken from
anywhere and used as
a like a leper and right because so he's
there's a difference is that he's
conscious of what's the process
what's happening well the thing is this
i think it's a scapegoat
mechanism that makes you kill a martyr
but in christianity the martyr is not
the scapegoat
in christianity the scapegoat the
marcher
he's not a role model about being killed
he's a role model and staying with the
faith yes no matter what
that's exactly what christianity won he
was incredibly i mean
it had a huge martyrdom culture in the
third of the fourth century
it was also way more violent and
territorial than people assume he wasn't
pacifist at all
but what christianity one was that
people just saw these guys were
impressed with them
but they weren't scapegoats and that was
also impressive there must be
there must be another mechanism right
here because christians knew
this was preach everywhere the die
christ died for us on the cross and he
took on
he was later said he took on our sins
but that was later thomas is right about
that
but the point was to to to make an end
of history an event
to the fact that christ was on the cross
so no other martyrs
on the cross could take the place of
christ on the cross no
but the other martyrs could be lesser
gods they could become saints in
christianity which catholicism and
orthodoxy used them for
as being look at this guy he he he had a
terrible
life he failed the things but he died
for his faith
he died believing in god all the way
through and therefore if you believe the
way he believed
your sins will be forgiven because of
christ on the cross we can move forward
now zoroastrianism deals with it
differently it wants to get rid of the
scapegoat mechanism for other reasons
because obviously
once we move away from a lynch mob
of a nomadic tribe and moving to some
kind of civilized settlement that we're
going to have long periods of peace and
trade with one another we don't want to
go to war all the time
we can't have constant lynch mobs in the
streets that's not a unique
insight to early christians or jews that
it must be a universal insight something
that indians and chinese and iranians
certainly dealt with too
now the way so raster dealt with that to
get it out of the way that's exactly why
michelle is not even a part of swarovski
culture
or they don't believe in sin to begin
with is
he basically said that let's just put
the corpses where they belong just just
declare them dead
period yeah so you cannot celebrate a
corpse
yeah so literally unclean i'm pure must
be thrown out of the community as
quickly as possible
and what they did they built this dork
moss and of course when you have desert
your vultures around you had vultures to
eat the corpses and that's all they did
that's just the corpse and they taught
their kids that's no longer grandfather
that's a grandfather it's gone and of
course in full religion that becomes a
separation
of soul from the body but that's not
part of serastrian teaching in itself in
zoroastrian teaching in itself
you die when you die like heidegger said
and you must live a full life until you
die hide again again called the harvard
and what you leave behind when you die
is that everything you achieved in your
life can be used by others to build
further civilization from it
and that's of course the base of the
persian empire and that's called amere
ancient person for transcendence meaning
what is beyond your death it's
not immortality it is you die but
through your mortality your life becomes
meaningful and precisely because you
leave heritage behind for your sons and
daughters to inherit
you made something meaningful out of
your life so you can't make
death sacred right no exactly
you can't and zoroastrianism you can't
make death a corpse sacred
that's what you're saying no acceptance
so the problem for perhaps with
scapegoating is disability or or
paganism is this ability to make death
sacred and so
exactly so we got the mausoleum of lenin
the mausoleum stalin under communism in
russia
pagan phenomena again we got this you
take the fucking corpse it becomes
pathetic and you're going there after 40
years and the skin's yolo
and it's all good plastic and there are
flies everywhere and it's just trying to
keep a corpse alive
yeah that's interesting i want to ask
thomas about that because
when you read girard you get the
impression that christianity is the only
the only thing that's ever been invented
that has been able to deal with the
scapegoat right
and that doesn't seem to be true i mean
because other cultures like
you know zoroastrianism and buddhism had
we're not overrun by the scapegoat right
yeah i'm sure lots of cultures were not
and then there are pagan cultures where
you know the scapegoat was rampant but
obviously these other cultures than
christianity
had a different way or or of
um you know controlling the scapegoat or
mechanism this is a very good question
and um i still haven't read the book but
gerard has written a book about the
vedic cultures as well
um it's about india and so religion in
india and
and so there he he sees he sees similar
uh
patterns also expose exposing the the
victimized mechanism things such as that
i haven't
read the book yet but he was aware of
this problem
and and he was looking at other cultures
but i agree that it's a pity that he
hasn't
investigated this more thoroughly um he
probably didn't have time uh
i mean the man of life right but but
this is very good
but i think that that people are
exaggerating this a bit
um i think that christianity is without
any doubt
the most spectacular example of the
exposure of the victim
mechanism that i know of buddhism does
something else buddhism goes to the
to the problem of desire because
basically the victimized mechanism comes
from the problem of desire right
and buddhism goes directly to desire but
it doesn't it doesn't
it doesn't explicitly expose this whole
mechanism like christianity does
not in the same way and so rasterism
basically is an heroic religion it's
completely phallic
so it doesn't allow victimhood at all
within the system
so you can't celebrate victimhood unless
you start celebrating drought and if you
celebrate druid
you're a heretic that's exactly what
it's so rasters of adamantly went after
the gnostics i mean they're murdered
victimhood outside of christian
influence right because
the the whole point is that christianity
makes it wrong to kill the scapegoat
so so that's why why we have so
basically all these all these
these uh mobs that are so that have
so-called concern for the victim
uh that's basically a form of perverted
christianity it's very obvious
gerard has also written about this it's
exactly because christianity is so
obsessed with protecting the victim
this has pervaded the entire world so
everybody is now super interested in
protecting the victim
and you get a lot of status from
protecting the victim this is
a christian idea this would would be
completely incomprehensible to romans
for example they would not give a fuck
there could be what about the
zoroastrians did the zoroastrians give
i mean yeah that's exactly is there
something is there something about
christianity that is
this that's so unique that gerard is
talking about
you know i don't have the answer no i
don't think there were a lot of
buddhists running around you know
i don't know like buddhists don't
sacrifice animals or you know well
hey cambodia was a buddhist country that
paul paul took over the 1970s and killed
two million of his countrymen so
obviously but that was my culture hey
wait a second
unless nobody studied marx in cambodia
not a single
i said that to provoke you a little bit
yeah no no no no no no no what is that
no i think sherrod is
going to say it's rousseau gerard is on
to something very profound here
the lynchburg mechanism is universal it
belongs to nomadologies it belongs to
the original universal religions we
practice for tens or hundreds of
thousands of years
it is it is in our genes it's something
we need to deal with constantly
i think gerard is absolutely right of
that and then we can look at cultural
studies and sales dealt with and i think
precisely the cultures that are innocent
to it and do not have an awareness of
the scapegoat mechanism and the lynch
bomb otherwise the most vulnerable to it
that's exactly what the maoist cultural
revolution killed
tens twenties thirties and millions of
people and cambodia was like two million
out of eight million died before paul
pogba stopped
so i think i think the cultures that
actually are not aware of this but with
the scapegoat mechanism it's something
you're born with
oh that's interesting so maybe buddhism
was was vulnerable because it didn't
have that
awareness that's interesting yeah but i
would say that
i said about christianity and buddhism
are unique in their own way right
i mean buddhism has has has investigated
the problem of desire itself to
to a really great extent where where
where because christianity basically
said like you know do not
do not follow these these patterns
because they are dangerous right so it's
a it's a very renunciate religion
basically
while buddhism kind of says like well
that's not gonna work
right so sutra is basically renunciation
right renunciation of anger and all
these negative things and stuff like
that but then you also have the layer of
tantra
which kind of acknowledges well you're
not going to get rid of that you have to
kind of creatively deal with all these
things that that that you would like
not to be there yeah that's something
that christianity did not develop to the
same extent
in my opinion well yeah because i but i
also have the intuition that that tantra
has very good ways of dealing with with
the scapegoat
on some level you know by by enacting it
dramatically and
like there's another there's a dramatic
enactment of uh you know standing on
corpses and things like that
or or or you know drinking alcohol and
you enact the desires right there's a
dramatic announcement which
frees you from the the this this uh this
mob uh sort of uh
you know uh the mob that would go for
the scapegoat but by
by by acknowledging it and seeing
yourself and but you know and
we got dialectics from the greeks on to
hegel in the west but he wasn't part of
christianity so
the dialectical means that you know it's
going to pop up somewhere it doesn't pop
up in your sex life that pop-ups in your
social life or somewhere else
you're just gonna come back to haunt you
so you better include it in your
livestream related certainly if you're
gonna be master of your own destiny you
have to include it
nietzsche's uh you know nietzsche is
adamant about this so it's freud and
that's because there's sounds of hegel
so that causes together dialectics in
the west and obviously that's something
that he's dealt with all along they do
that all along but
if if buddhism deals with desire
uh it also deals with suffering right
and the suffering
from your own desire and the fact that
suffering is so central to buddhism is
of course the strongest
card because so much of life is
suffering
and if you can deal with suffering
without turning you into victim whereas
the people you envy do not suffer which
then just fosters another lynch mob
so you must in buddhism declare that
suffering is universal
otherwise there's those who suffer and
those who do not and if that happens
then you get exactly the sort of class
revenge is some or or a group revenges
that dominates our culture today
yeah because if you can declare that i
suffer uh i've chose to suffer
i declare that i suffer and i am the
only one allowed to do that you cannot
say
speak against me and you don't suffer
because i didn't suffer
you take whatever i want away from you
there is suffering is the statement of
buddhism there is suffering it doesn't
say that
um yeah it doesn't doesn't point the
finger of suffering and also there's
three other
aspects to that that's just it's it's
just the beginning right now
people take that as the whole thing
right but it's just uh nobody
experienced why buddhism and
zoroastrianism gels so well against our
asthma
gels well with others because it
exclusively deals with certain things
it deals with the heroic it deals with
the phallic it is a building
civilizations
that's exactly what zoroastrianism deals
with and it doesn't claim to be the only
religion
it claims to be the first universal
religion in the sense that it's
universal religion for an elite
nobody assumed that you would have a
universal religion that all human beings
on the planet would inherit to
3700 years ago no you declared a certain
teaching
along the trade routes that people were
allowed to follow and if they did so you
promised they'd probably be successful
right okay that's where zoroastrian
comes in that's exactly what zoroastrian
is also the birth of universal human
rights
because they differentiated between the
elite religion that they eventually
divided into the priesthood religion and
the military religion
mithraism and zurbanism and they had a
false religion
which like well you can worship whatever
you like you're all going to worship
idols and celebrities and whatever
anyway
or at best christian saints much better
role models than jimi hendrix to be
honest about it
so the the the idea the lesser gods was
there in christianity at least the
catholicism and orthodoxy it escaped the
protestants that's exactly because they
were they were essentially cartesians
they're not christians
but he was there in catholicism and
orthodox and it makes sense
but looking at differently comparing
that the magical
the very feminine power of christianity
buddhism is something they share
and they did so apparently by buddhism
claiming that we know about suffering
and we deal with suffering so we also
deal with the origin of suffering which
is desire itself
that makes sense there are no
mythological concerns that's just a
normatological religion
what christianity had to deal with
though was that it came out of an
eventological landscape
since the sarasota side invented
eventology and later of course judaism
christianity islam also logical
religions linear time or incredibly
important isolation
spectacular events can change history
forever you could not have invented
christ
in the cradling you cannot invent the
christ on the cross unless
you could not have invented the more
translator would become saints and
lesser gods because of it
you could not have invented that unless
you believed events actually changed
history forever
and that idea is personal so the problem
is it seems that
when these systems then collide
without knowing about each other which
would happen when western eventology
suddenly boom got into east asia in the
1960s and 1970s
these societies incredibly vulnerable to
that
i mean it wouldn't be too hard if you're
a tyrant to say that you're all
suffering and by the way there are some
people who don't if people are told that
your
suffering is universal and you say but
there are some people who are not
and they're called capitalists now
there's not much of a tweak that's
needed by mao to actually say that right
and that becomes maoism
so i think we're at our most vulnerable
we leave history in our own culture
and we don't no longer understand and
haven't got a clue
of what we're approaching and then we
step right into it and then we cause
think we get to have what we currently
have
fundamentally understand in eventually
no matter all that you think is central
i
i think chirag is definitely in the
evantological
since he bases this on one scapegoat
could forever change
the landscapes of scapegoat will no
longer be needed that is an
eventological change to a nomadological
conviction
the normal logical conviction being if
you only find somebody to blame things
on we can get release and tensions out
of the way and we can move on and have a
period of peace until the next build
tension is built up now if you're
convinced that's the case if the shamans
are convinced that the case
the sooner or later we'll have to find
the scapegoat and the scapegoating
mechanism has to be in place
if you believe in homology that's
probably you would see so up
i'd expect chiron studies of india would
find that still to be the case in india
whereas with christianity because it
inherited
from zoroastrianism and judaism the idea
of eventology
it could come up with the idea that if
somebody dies on the cross we could
reinterpret that
as it's the end of the scapegoat
mechanism and see if we can make that
work
yeah then it's interesting to look at
the persian perspective of christ on the
cross
so the persian perspective is of the two
celestions i don't know if you've been
through this before but it's part again
of the social theory
which is the opposite of the tyrant
theory this ocean's precursor needed a
name
thomas and i've been talking about it we
eventually settled for the word hyperjet
i love the word superject but
unfortunately whitehead has already
claimed that and he uses it for his
subjectivity so
the white hidden subject is called the
superjet which is perfect the hyperjet
is the precursor to the savior
so the hyperjet is somebody who just
speaks up against the mob to begin with
says the voice
the voice of recent truth opposed to the
mob
you said there has to be two when it
appears
the hype the on object is one voice and
then the tolerance steps forward okay
could be one or two whatever uh but the
the
we're probably likely to just the priest
and the uh
uh the priest and the the warrior again
or
interesting this is where it gets
interesting high projection what is
higher projection then
high projection is basically looking
into the future and said
where are we actually going what is
possible
could the impossible be possible where
is the promised land how do we get out
of the current mess out of the current
suffering
and walk towards our desire which is the
promised land okay
how do we do that well you need an error
under moses you need a priest
what does the priest do he creates the
narrative there is a promised land
the promised land is full of milk and
honey if we just leave everything else
behind and we focus
on that one spot the name of that spot
is god
and we walk towards god we will arrive
at the promised land
now next that is the chieftain he
personifies the leadership
he steps forward and says that i
personify this
and i step up against the lynch mob
which is moses case was that i will take
you with me and leave egypt towards the
promised land
and of course the lynch mob in the bible
is of course in the pharaoh regrets that
he let the hebrews leave
and he puts himself on a horse and they
come storming down
and the red sea opens and the hebrews
can walk through
speaking of rebirth and then the red sea
closes and drowns the lynch mob
that clearly is the jewish lands bob the
jewish leadership obviously egyptians
will go after the hebrews and try to
kill them
yeah so there you go with the learnings
that's how the use deal with the
national mechanism is just not us
we should be educated sophisticated
enough in the jewish population
not to go into scapegoat mechanisms
right and that's how we stay away from
it because it's something others do but
we do not
because we're a nation and we're
superior that would be the jewish
version of it now the sorested version
of that would be that well
actually there are two different ways of
being associated if
you're so damn successful you actually
go against the lynch mob and they
dissolve
yeah and then you become a heroic
sergeant
and you win and then you retire
aristocle built the idea that eventually
personified and alexander the great on
that very id he borrowed it straight for
the purchase he was the person
associated
with alexander the great was of course
by the greeks at least declared
to be a savior right so you we have
these great heroes military heroes etc
throughout history clay claimed to be
first socials so you call them
but what's interesting with the person
is they would admit
that if the session fails he speaks the
truth
he speaks osha but the mob of drouge
go after him anyway and kill him
that would be the person saying okay
what do we do then well they put him on
a cross
and he died okay let's use that since
we're free to use the corpse any way we
like
let's use that as a story that says that
why don't we make
this killing of the savior himself
the hero was killed by us we kill the
hero what do we make that's the
ultimate learning lesson that we need to
learn a little bit less we need to learn
that this was never happened again
and that's where you have a connection
with jesus and christianity so
righteousness don't have a problem
christianity did you say
yeah they they they made their bet on
the second session as if he was the
final sergeant we don't we still think
the first ocean can come
i think i think these two versions are
perfectly compatible with each other
would you agree i i don't see the
difference
because basically okay so so christ
dying is basically well it exposes this
mechanism
let's not go there but anything else is
basically open right that's why gerard
also emphasizes that
the bible ends with the apocalypse which
is this very
strange text very psychedelic right it's
not exactly clear what it's about but it
basically means that if you remove this
victimage mechanism you are in trouble
because this victimish mechanism works
very well
yeah just keep the community calm oh
hell breaks loose sort of
before you get to the promised land
right for 2 000
years we have seen the collapse of the
victimh mechanism now it's suddenly back
because the internet brings everybody
together
and makes everything basically very
egalitarian societies where everybody's
uh connected they're actually very
vulnerable to the victimization
mechanism and we've killed christianity
as nietzsche said we would we have done
that
no we have killed christianity so we
don't have the christians
it seems collapse of christianity that
is something that
that's exactly what you what you expect
because basically this now the
victimization mechanism has really
collapsed
so there's no more burning of jews
there's no more burning of witches so
that kept to a certain extent
that sacrificial part of christianity
that kept that together
that's all gone now so now we are in a
very interesting
uh space where christianity cannot use
the victimized mechanisms anymore to
promote
this sacrificial form of christianity
and now basically the question is well
what next what are we going to do now
well we're killing we're killing sex
workers and drug addicts all kinds of
people in our society and a lot of old
people too because the coronavirus at
the moment but it's more and more
difficult right
no i don't say it's more difficult i
think we just moved the scapegoat to
somewhere else
and make somebody else this doesn't work
anymore because there's no unanimity
you can still i mean you can still go
after scapegoats but it's you do not
unite the tribe anymore
not everybody buys this anymore very few
people actually buy this most people
don't speak up but
nobody believes this story that somebody
this guy was completely guilty there's
that's not very believable anymore
certainly not among philosophers and
thinkers and stuff like that i mean
that's just
that train has gone so that's
but it's still operating it's so it's
still unconsciously operating
you know all over the place and probably
i'd be careful to say it's gone since a
pagan religious nazism plundered the
planet only 50 years ago and certainly
killed
millions of jews and gypsies and
everything so it i i'll be careful to
say it's gone already now
and we're tired of it and aware of it to
the extent thomas's claims
i don't think so i don't think well you
mentioned the apocalypse and i think the
apocalypse has to come first and then
you you get to the promised land or
something right
so what wait a second nothing has to
fall apart though
the whole thing just falls apart
completely and that's what this is the
return of christ psychedelic
weird andrew there's the return of
christ you can't complete christianity
without i don't know if she wrote us a
theory on it sherrod is not the only
christian after all i mean
and and after apocalypse christ returns
so this time around christ is the first
socio even christianity claims he has to
come back as the winner
so it's it's either another person or
somebody else taking the role but it's
certainly the proper savior who comes
back well the jews which are
such say that the christos kind of it
moves
through different different saviors
right and christ was sort of one of them
and
the cristos would move to the next one
it's not the man they say it's the wine
it's not the wine skin but the the wine
right um yeah the principle it's not a
personal principle
no there are there are prophets who
probably qualify for being saints or
martyrs or being savers or whatever
their prophets have that quality
there's a lot of people who just
happened to walk by and they said a few
things
and very little was remembered and
somebody else wrote the book about them
afterwards claiming they said things
they never said
muhammad didn't write a word he still
apparently authored the quran
i don't know how that happened right
probably a person wrote it not an arab
to begin with right
so you know we claim things afterwards
and attribute them to the corpses okay
human history is full of attribution
given to corpses
let's admit that we should even go into
maybe in details
to find out what kind of attributions do
we give to corpses
sometimes we cherish them sometimes we
just you know they go to pains decline
them evil
sometimes we blame things on them so we
don't need to take care of that
ourselves
all kinds of things we we we know that
corpses do not speak back
i think that's a great insight that's
universal that's why they're useful or
you know that's why they can't be used
or at least
at least to the defense or astronautism
they they realize that
let's just at least force people to only
memorize who they were
and maybe the more truthful rather than
celebrating the corpses themselves
so you know it's the partition of mind
and body does happen at death
um mind is collective anyway if it's a
collective might talk about rather than
individual mind
then certainly mind survives as the
collective anyway it's their language of
memory and everything else
but the body is literally dead in the
case the mind is connected to the body
which is of course your own
self-consciousness
then it's certainly over the sauron's
never claimed anything else they never
believed anything else they didn't spend
that's exactly why even if they were
wealthy successful they never built
pyramids
their tombs were very small and they
locked up their corpses and that was
only of the kings
the mobets themselves were thrown into
the deserts so the door kumas were
developed not originally
they were developed later as a response
to the egyptian
building of the pyramids and it was of
course economically credibly smart if
you're going to run an empire not spend
any more time on corpses
once people are dead just get rid of
them may i may i jump in there's
something
i want to come back to about uh you
mentioned the nazis right you said like
well
the victim edge mechanism isn't that
take for example the nazis
very very true excellent example of
basically a
an outbreak of of rampant paganism but
that's exactly what you expect because
if you dismantle
the victimage mechanism as coupled to
organized religion
right then it will come out in a
disorganized way that's why we now have
these mobs
online mobs of all kinds of all kinds of
sorts and shapes
and that's why we had nazism because
basically the the
the pagan mechanisms that are in us you
know every
in us all they are not regulated anymore
by religion
so they're just everywhere suddenly they
just break out that's the apocalypse
normally the pagan mob would be would be
guided by
by pagan religion so yes we're gonna
kill people but we're gonna kill the
right person at the right time in a good
ritual even the greek
did that you know the pharmacom which
you uh which you mentioned
uh a couple of episodes ago right the
greek they kept slaves
that they sometimes would kill the
civilized greek right
so and and so so basically they they
acknowledged that paganism
but they made sure that it was regulated
but christianity basically dismantled it
decoupled it from religion
but of course that mechanism is still in
us so we know it's wrong and we don't
want to go there and and
for 2000 years we've seen that this is a
a very destructive way of being
but we go there again and again we can't
help ourselves and that's the apocalypse
that's why we live in a secular society
as the apocalypse that's
kind of interesting huh because we would
think it's like oh it's it it it's
being advertised to be the opposite
right so
it could be some kind of liberation from
from religion but uh so
wrong but uh very wrong oh nietzsche
said that all andrew you you
you said that too yeah needs to say that
all along andrew you can't forget about
nietzsche
forget about the new york times said we
don't even discuss shit like that we
talk about nietzsche for example
nietzsche nietzsche said you've killed
god and you've done it
you will regret it and he caught blood
everywhere wait a second
millions of corpses and now what he sees
today is the last man syndrome so we see
the last man everywhere in his most
pathetic version too
i wouldn't even call it the last man i
call it the last child
if anything we're seeing today this is
last child culture
and uh yeah it's it's gonna get really
messy and
last child last man means the you know
the the the kind of the nihilist the guy
who's
yeah exactly come become yeah total
night meaning um
yeah and if you put any sort of energy
even destructive energy or more t
though death drive into the last man or
the last child for that matter
you get the current mass you get exactly
woke you get all this shit that's going
on it's gonna get worse you got joker
and
zombie yeah yeah yeah yeah tyrants
post-modernism right i mean i mean i'm i
think it's
very much uh worthwhile to study
thinkers like the laws and focus and
stuff like that are not going to be
be very simplistic about it but a lot of
the pop interpretations of
post-modernism i think that's the last
man
embodied yeah that's
why spinosa without hegel gets so
destructive
that's where it comes from explain okay
so if you take spinoza seriously and you
see his weaknesses you discover that
spinosa
insists that the world is one
but because there is different he then
just subtly attributes that to really
attribute to the attributes he just
basically says that tons of attributes
it doesn't explain how the the one and
the attributes
collaborate with one another how they
function in relation to one another
because nothing can be infinite
unless it is everything in in any system
because otherwise it isn't infinite
so so you've got lots of problems with
spinosa can't
imalicant actually is the great critic
of spinoza
he tears him apart he tears apart that
shit
and after that spinoza is wonderful as
an inspiration to study monism
he's certainly wonderful as an
inspiration to study how you can put
attributes into the monastic universe
but at the end of the day the universe
does exist of different things for
example a rock and human consciousness
are very different things
they're not just attributes we talk
about we talk about as emergence vectors
in our theory
it's a radically radical spheres that
are separated from one another although
they belong to the same neutrally modest
universe
this is all very complex being also
didn't really go into the complex of it
but spin also lacks dialectics again he
lacks a dialectical understanding of the
world
this of course is what hegel's critique
was being also hegel allowed spinoza as
we should
but then said but there's tons of shit
lacking in spinoza
and one of them is that he doesn't
understand dialectics rather than
pantheism which is what spinosa features
then hegel creates pan-dialecticism
meaning that everything both physical
biological and mental whatever is
dialectical fundamentally dialectical
and it's been proven right again and
again and again and again that's why
there's a great hegelian renaissance the
g-shape there's adrian johnston there's
people like me who read hegel all the
time
we love hegel and i think that's the
concept of the negativity or something
no no negativity negation being certain
an enormous difference you must not
ever ever use positive and negativity
when you talk about dialectic
nation negation is like buddhist
emptiness somehow and then that
yes that allows the whole system to
become fluid and alive rather than being
some kind of
you know realified monism or
this is exactly okay so hegel is you're
finishing difficult but brilliant beyond
belief
so you read hegel through whitehead if
you're smart today you read
whitehead through hegel and you're
probably the two most
interesting spheres you could possibly
study today if you do philosophy
now that excludes binosa why
because hegel took kant's criticism spin
also seriously and moved on and
put a proper dialectics into the
universe so that means that hegel what
people constantly forget is also
modest there's only one universe but
what he realized is this universe
operates dialectically
everything operates dialectically which
then he solves all the problems fit also
left behind
now the problem is that in the 1960s
people were hippies right
now hippies influenced thinking and art
and everything way more than we assumed
because a lot of people want to be
trendy and cool and fashionable
these were like bad monists no so
post-modernists are always people to end
up with turtlenecks in art galleries
aren't they discussing philosophy
right so it's like the germans in in the
saturday night live show in america the
1980s there were like turtlenecks and
had a german accent and they were
dancing
funny coughed walkish dance in berlin
and they were you're blaming that
ultimately on spinoza i mean no no
no i'm blaming no i'm blaming the
spinner system
i was the first hippie or something no
wait is it i'm blaming the spin assist
revival
that we saw with the lures in the 1970s
and with postmodernism
i'm saying that we cannot read spinosa
and ignore
kante lenix who came after him because
what these guys are doing is that
they're going back to spinoz and
pretending
imano can't never happen
that's like that's like that's like
believing the earth is flat
right the the revolution of khan changed
his philosophy forever at least in the
west
we saw red traces of it before these but
never before in the west
and you cannot re you cannot not read
the greeks you cannot read christianity
you cannot read anything unless you see
this tremendous revolution
now what hegel did was that he then he
then turned count against himself by
saying that
the con separation of the numeral of the
phenomenon is kind of ridiculous too
we might as well move everything into
the phenomenological pharmacological to
begin with
because dengan seiko is removed by hegel
which is fantastic
so hegel introduces process philosophy
to the west
through dialectics the pan dialecticism
of hegel is the pan organicism
awaited and avoid pan psychism at all
costs because pan psychism is
essentially what spinoza is
so pan psychism where does that appear
in france in the 1960s and in california
in the 1960s
in california the 1960s culturally in
in france in the 1960s more
philosophically speaking
and these two then blended and one
worship was exported across the atlantic
to america
and became pomo and the other ones
exported back to europe became
essentially
you know the guys the art colors of the
turtlenecks you know the pretentious
philosophers that i always disliked in
europe
so that's pomo and pomo is
to a large extent vulgar spinal system
vulgar in the sense that it's too close
to spinoza's original teachings
without taking content hagel seriously
i've i've never heard
that i've never heard about the sling
between spinoza and uh
and post-modernism i i know that count
and post-modernism have been linked but
uh
no no not at all no can't no they fight
with kant all the time today it's called
speculative realism it's been the
dominant mode for the past 20 years
and graham harman and all these guys are
into speculative realism
and they also believe they can get
beyond kant by going back to the
pre-conscience
i don't think they can at all you can't
go back to the pre-content it's just
impossible
we know that the moment of the phenomena
are always separated but so what
what is the new part you do know that
white hat
both white hat and heidegger basically
their uh their program is to to get the
phenomenon and the nominee
to get that idea out of the philosophy
right
come on very much uh how do you get the
kind of agreement with this country
heidegger becomes a german country point
when he tries to do that you can't do
that
you've got to go through the hegel in
that case okay heidegger does it better
when he just imitates angle
but what what you do is that you move
into phenomenology period and that's
what hegel did and then he realized
everything is dialectical you can go
back and then study
science and mathematics and logos how
much as you like and discover is
dialectical too
everything changes all the time that's
fundamental right
so without going too much into those
details i think
i think we need to if you're going to
criticize the lust at its weakest points
and the last is the one i will say
lockhart is not part of homo lacon is a
hegelian through and through let's get
the khan of the big that's exactly why
people like me and shishek and johnston
are reading lacan reading hegel and
we're reading gerard and we really need
it
but if pomo was just a vulgarization a
pop philosophy of some kind appearing in
the 1970s and france and america
will we have promised it for cohen to
lose certainly with the later demons
certainly with the latest the lesser
guadalee they hate
i think they're bringing it back like
maybe it's a parody of nietzsche
i mean even the way they write right i
mean i'm reading derrida now which is
great i mean it's like
reading a sacred text it's like reading
the bible they got that from nietzsche
also was practical he was the guy who
started this this tradition
and so a lot of post-modernism i mean i
i like reading these these texts in the
sense that you know i'm very at home i'm
i'm used to reading long champa and
stuff like that
these guys are writing uh secular sacred
texts
especially
and they never read hegel properly they
read hegel through hippolyte or kojav
only indirectly well jeff yeah right
yeah that means that the lastest
critique of hegel is his weakest point
and the problem is that he disguises it
with spidosa worship
so that means he he goes for espinosa
without hegel hager wrote a lot about
spinoza
hegel had a fellow called shelling and
shouting was
who was then converted into hegelian
during his own lifetime
if you read the older shelling you go
back to the younger shelling you see
enormous differences between the two
so shelling was the spinosist after kant
who tried to go back to spinoza and
escape kant when he's not too
philosophia
hagen knew that was impossible laughter
said no kant made a revolution let's go
even dig even deeper
and let's turn kant against khan what
would kanta said about khan critically
and that's where hegel moved wonderfully
in the early 1800s with his amazing
philosophy
he's still the greatest guy i just have
a question i want to try to
if we can bring this back to the lynch
mob idea a little bit
okay are you are you are you
connecting a false reading of spinoza
like to to let's say to the 60s america
and to the postmodernist
and to the present lynch mob situation
can you like
is that what you're doing yeah because
and can you can you like
call it vulgar spinner system and vulgar
spinner system is just
pop philosophy that hasn't studied this
shit that's california new h2
oh everything is united with everything
okay the world is one
and we're all sitting here together and
if you only listen to each other and
listen
in to each other we say we'll all be
peaceful and there'll be no antagonisms
between us and no class differences
and all we need to do is decide then you
move that into woke culture as practiced
by woke
people it's the same shit that's how
woke meetings are the same talk
but they add some anger to it by having
an outside escape goal they can blame
so you take california new age or vulgar
spinal system which is pomo
and then you put that into context when
you just add some electricity to it by
basically telling a 22 year old girl
that
oh by the way it's a 47 year old why my
man outside is a white heterosexual
he's a working-class guy and refuses to
commit the revolution oh i can go after
him he's my scapegoat and off they go
with their pagan
scapegoat mechanisms that's exactly what
we're seeing today
yeah okay so that's as if almost guilty
of creating woke
it's a precursor to woke yes is poem a
vulgar yes it is because it's
essentially vulgar spanish system that's
what it is
and that's what you get if you read
spinoza too literally
and believe he speaks directly to you
and your little spider's a genius
and you're not actually reading the
amazing critiques
constructive critiques of the honored
spinoza
that were written by kant and hegel and
the other guys in the 1800s
you can't you can't do this so what's
the thing that hey
what's the thing that uh sorry about
this what's the thing that um
uh con changes what is
can you explain that what's the step
from spinoza to khan's
transcendental dialectics transcendental
yeah okay so he does dialectics and he's
he's seriously considering the
difference between
my here and and that thing there that in
itself divides the world between the
normal and the phenomenon
so the unity this sort of romantic unity
of spinoza's universe
disappears also spinosus is god has a
will we have no wealth the promise
there's no wealth to power in spinoza
you will don't will anything andrew i
don't wield
anything thomas doesn't will anything
and this idea of a sort of passive
subjectivity that just floats around
here and there
damasio used to be spinoses but he
turned against but also interestingly
enough of the 2010s that's interesting
to see
how he started saying no no no the
vulgar spinner system wasn't what i
meant with spinosa being back in fashion
and rereading spin also that's a good
idea if you're a competitive scientist
the demacia's too smart for that he
turned against that there's no
contingency in the universe of spinoza
so basically there is there is there is
god that knows everything the past and
the future that means that there is no
real
there's no real contingency if you would
run the universe if you stop the
universe here you would run it again so
to speak then you would get the same
outcome there's no
it could not be otherwise so that's
that's the the block universe of spinoza
and it's the universe of einstein as
well
einstein it is yeah it is is but but
can you see also in the vulgarized
version how attractive that is to
hippies
we don't want to commit themselves to
anything because it takes an effort to
make a commitment
oh yeah accept what is and stuff like
that yeah yes yeah
and and all this there's a lack of i'm
getting a lack of masculinity too i'm
getting
oh totally you're getting a lack of
energy uh in in the uh
okay so nietzsche's response to that is
of course will the power
yeah okay the way to do that take it
seriously now is to divide will to power
again split phallus into world's
intelligence will the transcendence
and because machines will not have will
to transcend us they'll own their
world's intelligence
we can make the machines operate
beautifully for the priests but at the
same time we achieve chance actually god
lead and create society as a work of art
and that would cry
require without transcendence this is
way away from spinoza
and this is where de la struggles with
dominology and everything he did in his
last 10 years
in that actually if there was a delusion
heritage
yeah he could be interesting for
complexity science and pretentious art
or whatever but but if you're gonna if
you're gonna you're gonna make something
forceful out of the lust and his desire
originally was younger was to be
nietzsche
and i loved the lessons 1960s work i
would definitely say difference of
repetition
and and uh uh the sunspot
theory says i would save those books
from the logical sense i would save
those books from what comes later
um the last denison clearly tell us
i i love and adore and i think he opens
up needs to to an event a logical
interpretation on issue which i use a
lot in my work
but i don't find these sort of grandiose
focus 5000 plateaus at all as useful now
as they were thought to be in the 1980s
i think actually
going down the john dew and de la
squattery
uh path towards education for youth
would be disastrous today it'd just be
hippie all over
anthropo anthroposo anthropocene you
know it's just anthroposophical
it's philosophical it's just it's just
trippy down it's just you elaborate a
bit on that
what are what are dewey you mentioned
dewey and dolores and they have ideas on
education is that correct
yeah and and and it's to today
when the world's falling apart become a
chaotic order in schools is more
important than ever
again dialectical if if the world is
chaotic
even more important to teaching the
world is you know
if the word is ordered you can elaborate
on like letting your kids be
be more loose and experimental so i i
would say that's a perfect example of
where it's not very useful to go towards
the lesser glottary today
and of course even if thousand plateaus
is a great
book an interesting great book if the
crap that comes afterward i hate heart
and negri and their empire broken shit
like that
it's a crap that comes afterward they
who call themselves neospinosis by the
way
i'm not a big fan of islam but do either
a certain amount of heart negativity and
that stuff that comes
afterwards altoser
if you have a problem today with
neo-marxists it's probably alpha syrians
you're talking about you're talking
about spinosauruses who claim to be
marxists
that's who we all have to say louis
althouser the grandfather awoke
then comes la clone move for long in the
1980s with the hedge money book
that is the bible of the world culture
today judith butler they're all
responsible for that
and it all goes back to vulgar's fellow
physicism that avoids
content especially loyola giggle is the
nasty word that should be used today
aggressively
and thankfully guys your favorite
whitehead and hegel are
very closely aligned to one another read
them through each other and you get them
both i mean
to me hegel and whitehead are oh
so i can't i can't add hegel to the
mixture there's no time
oh okay well you become the white
candidate i've been reading hegel i
i have a rough time of it i have to
admit uh giant reading hey girl i am
reading it but
very slowly i think adrian johnston's
doing a great job at this and some of
these ideas are obvious this is mine
as much as they're mine old i've seen it
coming for years too we've been in
dialogue for years i think adrian is
incredibly underrated because he's the
only american continental philosopher
but his continental philosophy is
brilliant
and he's a hegelian but he's also
defending something i don't defend which
is transcendental materialist i mean i
find it interesting there's there's much
more marxism in adrian johnson's work
than i would ever admit to
well we're thinking dialogue is
interesting here very interesting what
about heidegger here i was thinking
about
like uh i was thinking why i lean
towards heidegger and thomas leans
towards um
white whitehead and i was wondering like
people who have a kind of mystical like
i lean towards mysticism right
and and people who have have a kind of
like more scientific thing
lean more towards whitehead am i
[Music]
i'm a social philosopher he was highly
good now and then but you know the
good old nuts he's not very useful for
social philosophy he's very introverted
it's
very much how you experience the world
and you always end up thinking that
yeah you could experience the world
heidegger describes it and he does that
really well but
that's probably just hydrogen if you had
agarius actually do
experience the world that way so whereas
whitetail is much more neutral he's just
i have a question about heisenger so
he's so heidecker is basically from
phenomenology right he describes
what it is like to be human in a very
unusual way so you can kind of get a new
perspective on it
but to what extent does does he actually
have a metaphysics because whitehead is
a very suspect he's against metaphysics
i mean
isn't he isn't he trying to try to
destroy metaphysics
on some level they've pointed out that
you know i know
heidegger has a metaphysics and i was
got a bit of sure
heidegger said he didn't have a
metaphysic said he hated it but he used
the word metaphysics in a very original
sense
it was a certain history that he was
supposed to he was very grandiose when
he was young and he wanted to kill it
i'm not an opposite to the less i'm
actually think sign in sight is a bit
overrated
i've read it when i was young and i was
inspired by it but since i didn't want
to become a pretentious poet it wasn't
really for me
so but i love the old heidegger and i
know thomas got a start of the nietzsche
books that he wrote in the 1960s
i think the older heidegger is way more
interesting and he sometimes
nails things beautifully i mean he's
he's an oscar wilde at
you know an oscar while without the
sense of rhythm it's fun to read i think
it is fun to read well that's the only
reason you know i read but
that you cannot create a hydrogen system
to describe the internet age or the
network society
it's useless i can use heidegger to
discover that tasman
is the origin of the attract because
that's actually lacking in gerard's
theory because he didn't look into the
precursors
fine girard didn't have to now the
theory becomes more complete and i can
also make both an exodus and a
verticidology
by discovering that the anarchic must
then have a precursor to the savior
so where is the origin of the savior is
he christ in the cradle no but christ in
the cradle was probably symbolically
very important
to declare that the precursor would come
they could be on the baptism somebody
else prefers to
but the precursor is the guy who steps
up against the lynch mob
so john the baptist's head on the plate
is clearly a precursor to the messiah in
christian mythology
so that's why the hyperdect
is where i'm going next in my studies to
conclude the exodus
and then the priest if you're the first
saw sound like moses you don't go into
the promised land
almost symbolically you switch from
first to second solution by dying before
you enter the promised land
but you do send the chieftain into the
promised land because he's the physical
guy actually leads them into the
promised land because for you the
journey was the only thing that was
important
and that's typical for celsius for the
celsius
his only interest is to complete his
work
and his work is to stop the lynch mob
and make people realize
this is a fantastic golden opportunity
in history to do exactly the opposite
thing of lynch mobbing
which is to leave the lynch mob get out
of it
and walk in the opposite direction into
the promised land and be heroic
right and so that's why i'm interested
in
phallic because the phallic is
ultimately what is
lacking today not even religion but
phallic religion itself is lacking and
that's where i want to work
that's what we're completing our trilogy
with the exodus
first synthesis yeah we have the false
dionysian right
oh we have that still yeah the falston
has an end authentic dynasty
or basically it's the kick that you get
from joining the mop right so that's
this dionysian feeling that's this you
know
the the the frenzy of the kill now
via facebook right i mean look i wrote
this i
wrote this first i got him so that's
this dionysian feeling but it's of
course the fake dionysian right this is
kind of like a very
very bleak and and uh and unrewarding
form of the dionysian
describe the real dionysian then the the
the good dionysian
that's this aesthetic sort of communitas
where you get a burning map
burning man right yeah yeah yeah it's
bernie man it is
it is paradigmatically heroic
as a collective effort so it is
um dionysian is crowd
but this is crowd rather than mob and
it's crowded in the sense that it takes
on the heroic
why burning man works is because you
have to make an effort for yourself to
go there you have to make an effort to
survive
it's called radical self-expression
radical self-reliance if the principle
radical cephalic wasn't there burning
man would be another lynchburg probably
and then fail
but it stays and goes on year after year
after year has 200 copper cats around
the world again mimicking works here as
well
and these are authentically dionysian
very nice so
these are the festivals and the
carnivals of religion where you
celebrate yeah incredible
carnival carnival carnival is authentic
dynasty exactly
gotcha carnival yeah but but the exodus
would be apollonian wouldn't it
it it requires organization commitment
faith it requires priest it requires
chieftain requires a hell of an effort
that's exactly like smaller lead to
actually perform the exodus you don't
live in the dionysian this this is an
event a diagnosis should always be like
limited in time otherwise it kills you
basically i think that yeah
festival days like you know burned up
because he lived constantly in the
dionysian in the end he actually
realized that he did it because he
started
he started uh writing uh the crucified
right he identified actually
in the end with jesus which is he said i
am the crucifier didn't he
just killed me uh so that that's a very
interesting turn he took at the end of
his life
gerard also writes about that it's very
fascinating
these two guys you know gerard and
nietzsche we should have had them in the
same room and
and uh let them have a discussion oh god
and why ted
i i don't know why ted would just drink
the ultimate nerd the ultimate
he's too much of a nerd i was thinking
that too i think
gerard's a bit of a nerd too nietzsche
doesn't belong on any other planet
except his own
i would i would have loved hegel because
he was actually incredibly successful
and flamboyant and fun
during his own lifetime he became a
multimillionaire in germany why don't we
train
ai from hegel manuscripts yes scripts
and then we start we let them talk to
each other
yeah they resurrected from the dead
yeah we have to resurrect all of these
all these souls and
put them on the aisles and talk to each
other just like you know microsoft did
that with some kind of
book that was trained from uh from a lot
of example texts and stuff like that
right
so that might that might actually work
yeah and we could resurrect call schmidt
see whether he'd be naughty or not yeah
we throw a white heidegger in there and
stuff like that we have to do like a
futurama we have to lock their heads up
in a cabin or somewhere they won't get
bodies so just they just uploaded
and we resurrect 200 philosophers and we
just let them discuss for a million
years which we can
probably execute in one hour i have to
discuss this with simon chrisley and
finally getting back to work
on a follow-up to his amazing book dead
philosophers
resurrected philosophers is next that'd
be a great idea
there's the monty python skit with all
the philosophers playing football have
you seen that one
yeah yeah oh yeah oh yeah classic yeah
but i i well you can study hegel or
white to the rest of your life and they
they're richly rewarding when you do it
and i love both guys to bits but
i i would insist that just philosophy
and
the relationalism of why ted looks more
and more like the pine dialecticism of
hegel to me the more i read them
oh yeah but it's true bradley right so
whitehead was
in he claimed he never read hegel but he
read bradley
and bradley was the british interpreter
of hegel
um and so that's that's the connection
between between whitehead and hegel
and again that is a very uncorrupted
version because the problem with
hegelianism in europe was that it was
either through koja for hippolyta in
france
the french took overhead in the 1940s
obviously germany wasn't ruins
so we only got these different hippolyte
and kajiev readings
it wasn't until la khan and we finally
got
a proper hegelian reading that he opened
up to and that's exactly why
hegelians like uh me and and johnston
and and
zlavoishi sheikh and alicos and
countries are all coming out of the
makoni school and we're hegelians
that that makes perfect sense this is
this is a hegelian reading that's way
closer to nietzsche and whitehead
as it should have been all along but you
know hegel had
actually had a theory of desire that was
very close to gerard's but his was
this was a diet instead of a triad so
you want to be desired by somebody else
well while the desire of
girard is a is a triad right
there's always a third third wheel in
there yeah yeah
but would hagel need a third wheel since
he was dialectical anyway in anything
i think so yeah i think that this this
is a uh
he saw he had a very important insight
hegel but gerard kind of
um he he uh he perfected it yeah
great i'll look into that oh one more
thing before we finish tonight
the martyrdom thing so is martyrdom
universal or is it exclusive for only
some religions where it pays off
and who's the martyr really because the
marcher can be both
really nasty and incredibly well
incredibly wonderful and respected human
beings i think the romans didn't have
this
i think this is a christian thing and an
abrahamic thing
abrahamic thing i think it feels like an
abrahamic thing to me yeah
it's like you have to go through your
torture chamber and stay with your god
even if you're being tortured otherwise
you're not a martyr
then the saurus don't have martyrdom
either they don't have a word for it
there's not much
martyrdom in buddhist texts you know
there's there's
just it's it's kind of a unclean there's
something about it that is
if somebody if somebody puts a knife
against my throat
and threatens to kill me if i don't
declare myself to be non-seration i can
say that i'm a non-zoroastrian
and those are asians nobelians would
accuse me of anything because i need
threatening
the worship of death right that's what
no no no no no no
no no no it's a worship of a certain
principle
that is incredibly strong and attractive
though i have to admit that
you obviously martial don't work for
christianity it may be popular and
and he created a whole pantheon of
saints which is incredibly useful you've
got all the lesser gods of catholicism
for the next two thousand years from
marshall because martyrs obviously the
vast majority of saints are martyrs one
way or the other
so it was very useful for christianity
whereas our astronauts have dragged
along the folk religion for as long as
it lasted you know with anahita worship
and things like that
um which made so rest isn't better
for inclusion meaning you got a
pluralistic society
power sharing and you're going to have
different levels like you can have an
elite religion here and you kind of fall
collusion here which is just like india
operates it's just brahmanism and
hinduism
and that became like zurbanism and folks
or rasterism
but but the problem with that is that
you do not actively replace the pantheon
of the lesser gods which christianity
did and instead put the martyrs on there
and find them very useful
church paintings and everything well
also i think that the writers
like if you read the lives of the saints
the martyrs are always they're always
they have they're always morally pure
they always have this
there's you know there's everything
about them is perfect there's there's
this
idealization no no no no no no no no no
no no compared to like like the
when i read about it there are no such
people
they're always they used to be like uh
you know
murderers and killers and no no
christianity is the same we started with
cars
wait a second starting with saint paul
paul persecuted the jews and killed them
and went after them and then
on the road to damascus he became saint
paul no christianity is foreign
it's full of people who all
transcended themselves by staying
true with their faith even through death
and torture
the martyrdom is precisely the human who
goes beyond being human but stays human
in the process
christians will be adamant that martyrs
are nobody's perfect everybody's a
center in christianity
there was a sinner in christianity
everybody's saying that there are no
people no they're not role models to
look up to because of their lies
the romans to look up to because the
principle stands on the faith itself
okay but it does seem to be a um a
copying of jesus christ right so let's
do it again
and it's kind of ignoring the fact you
know the gospel is the good news
it's kind of like you know jesus did it
for you he did it once and for all
showed the victimized mechanism it's
done it's written down he's done it for
you so it's a new kind of nemesis this
new kind of imitation that's
taking over like like a kind of a
certain i mean it is a certain uh
it is a certain wanting to be the savior
yourself as well right
there could certainly be those cases
yeah that's why i'm saying them some of
the martyrs were obviously narcissistic
assholes
and some of the martyrs were probably
fantastic people to look up to
and it's probably the same with the
saints in that case and then
islam also again we can use the corpses
for whatever we would like and
christianity has done so very creatively
over the past 2000 years
probably mother teresa wasn't a very
nice person at all
but you know at the end of the day
corpse could be used for good purposes
for the church
and they gladly did so so there's a
certain cynicism
in the in the usage of corpses after
they're dead
because we have the liberty to do
whatever we like with them they're dead
after all
right we do what we want with the
heritages
so we do so which which is fine i
i think pr i think thomas's christie of
martyrs
being narcissistic copycats of christ on
the cross in those cases where it's true
is a classic
protestant critique of catholicism
and it makes sense it makes sense it
just made catholicism
so much richer religion islam they seem
to love
they love martyrs and islam as well too
don't they isn't that
something that you you would you would
want to be a martyr like you would you
would just train to be a martyr and
that would be your you would have that
as a goal right yeah but they don't have
the same tooth that you have in
christ in catholicism because you're
more or less guaranteed if you're a
martyr and somebody saw you die
right i i i i go to paradise you're
looking for the author
but i'd be careful to have that's
exactly a martyrdom i might even leave
it out of the book
it's a very very very interesting topic
and it probably fascinates because
erastism
doesn't think much of it it certainly is
a huge part of islam and it says islam
has mimicked
his rationalism to a large extent they
got it from gnosticism or something like
that it's
something gnostic about martial and yeah
but i i'm not an expert in islamic
martyrdoms at all
moderates at all um and certainly
haven't figured out the relationship
between the gnostic and the martyr
it's probably a nasty one um so
yeah martyrdom um with respect to
uh triangular desire so
you have to kind of take a look at for
example things like sado masochism
um because because it you will probably
find the explanation there
so girard has some very interesting
theories and
that basically explains why do people
for example adopt say the massachusetts
relationships
uh and uh or or for example the
relationships of
of uh uh you know a cult follower and a
guru
so these are these are basically
elementary um
elementary outcomes of of triangular
desire
yeah that's getting closer i think that
it's
yeah i think and there's a nasty side to
that whole thing with sort of
masochistic narcissism
leading up to martyrdom certainly but uh
i'm sure the people who were
just scapegoated and happened to be nice
people and and
who refused to you know at the end of
the day if you're being tortured and you
go through suffering you're probably
gonna die
and they tell you to resign from your
faith and the guys stand in front of you
are just ugly idiots it's just like why
would you give it to them they're gonna
kill you anyway you might as well stay
with the faith
that's probably how most martial dumbs
actually occurred you know so
um but is it interesting the stories are
always told in a heroic way right
yeah exactly meteorology is it's a topic
open to our students to explore if they
like to
i think i i think i i think i'm fine
with starting the associate and the
resurrection of the followers for the
new book
and then off i go i just i'm turning 60
next year i'm ready for commentary with
cigars and cognac
and so young ceticus says the same thing
we'll see what happens next but we're
going to write a fucking bible at least
first
processing event we're working on it and
i'm thrilled of having these discussions
with you guys and credit you for your
inputs
so gerard and whitehead that's a great
combination
that's the and hegel nature
is already in there so who needs ego but
you know yeah
white hat gerard that's kind of like the
triad i would like to see in a book
uh yeah we got our own pantheon there
don't forget like chimpa but anyway
and uh we'll read the red right i mean
we need some lesser gods too guys okay